<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Account of the seizing or apprehending, behaviour, confession, and commitment to Newgate of Mary St. Dunstan (born near Temple-bar), the bloody midwife's servant committed by warrant from the right honourable Sir John Fleet, knight, Lord Mayor : with an account of reasons for the midwife's poysoning of her self in Newgate.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75648</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A382A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173165</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077443</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077443</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151502</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75648)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151502)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2261:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Account of the seizing or apprehending, behaviour, confession, and commitment to Newgate of Mary St. Dunstan (born near Temple-bar), the bloody midwife's servant committed by warrant from the right honourable Sir John Fleet, knight, Lord Mayor : with an account of reasons for the midwife's poysoning of her self in Newgate.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Wallis near the Green Dragon Tavern in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed according to order."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>St. Dunstan, Mary.</term>
               <term>Fleet, John, --  Sir, d. 1712.</term>
               <term>Women murderers --  Great Britain --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:151502:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN ACCOUNT of the Seizing, OR Apprehending, Behaviour, Confeſſion,</hi> and <hi>Commitment</hi> to <hi>Newgate. OF</hi> MARY St. D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NSTAN, (<hi>Born near</hi> Temple-bar) The Bloody Midwifes Servant, Committed by Warrant from the Right Honourable, Sir <hi>John Fleet,</hi> Knight, Lord Major. With an Account of Reaſons for the Midwife's Poyſoning of her ſelf in <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>Licenſed According to Order. <add>13. Sept. 1693.</add>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>SInce the taking and commitment to <hi>Newgate</hi> of <hi>Mary Compton</hi> the Bloody Midwife of <hi>Poplar,</hi> all the care and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry imaginable has been uſed by the Maſters of the Pariſh of <hi>Poplar,</hi> the Beadles of St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> and other Pariſhes for the Apprehending of Mrs. <hi>Mary,</hi> the Servant of the ſaid Midwife; She laying all her Crimes on the ſaid Maid. By the Induſtry of the Searchers ſome ſmall Intelligence was got of our Mrs. <hi>Mary</hi> ſome days ſince by which She was ſo traced, that yeſterday being <hi>Monday Sept. 11th.</hi> She was apprehended by <hi>Thames ſtreet</hi> near <hi>London-Bridge,</hi> and by Conſtables carried before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, and before his Lordſhip, She was Examined, where She continued very obſtinate and impudent, her Miſtreſs having taught and tutored her in all her Paces; His Lordſhip asking her, her Name, all that She would confeſs, as to that particular, was, that her Name is <hi>Mary,</hi> and by no means She could be brought to any other, ſaying, She knew no other Name She had, or ever was call'd by; which is not improbable, conſidering that this Creature has lived with the Midwife from a Child, and the Neighbours where the Midwife forme<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly lived, looked upon this Maid to be ſome By-blow or Baſtard; and as 'tis ſuppos'd preſerv'd and brought up by her Miſtreſs on purpoſe to be an Inſtrument and Confederate with her in her horrid Practices: During her being before the Lord Mayor, ſeveral Affidavits were taken by his Lordſhip, on the Account of her being Confederate with her Miſtreſs the Midwife, in murthering divers young Children (as the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Narrative treats off) upon which She was committed to <hi>Newgate</hi> by Warrant or <hi>Mittimus,</hi> under his Lordſhips Hand and Seal.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Newgate</hi> She is kept apart from her Miſtreſs, then not being ſuffer'd to converſe with each other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poſtſcript.</hi> Since her being in <hi>Newgate</hi> her right Name is known, being <hi>Mary St. Dunſtan,</hi> by which Name She was Chriſtened, being a foundling of <hi>St. Dunſtan</hi>'s Pariſh in the Weſt, by whom She was put out to the Midwife, about Sixteen years ſince; She is about Eighteen years of Age.</p>
            <p>We ſhall now proceed to our Narrative of the Midwife, <hi>Mary Crompton,</hi> who many years ſince having the Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of an Eminent Midwife, was by her Inſtructed, and has Practiſed the ſame for a long time; and for many Years She has alſo us'd to take Children, always making her Bargain to have ſo much Money in hand for the bringing them up; what Nurſe She proved to them, the following Account Relates: Her real Practice as to laying of Women with Child has <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een very Inconſiderable, She liv'd for a conſiderable time at <hi>Wolwich</hi> by <hi>Greenwich,</hi> where She kept an Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe and Chandlers-ſhop, and there She made pretenſions to Midwifry the better to manage her damnable Deſigns on Children. She came to live at <hi>Poplar,</hi> which is near <hi>Stepney,</hi> about Two Years ſince, taking a large Houſe, where none but Perſons of conſiderable Rank had li-ved before, bringing with her at firſt only a Maid Servant, going for a Midwife of great note to Perſons of Quality; here ſhe had not continued long, before ſhe was obſerved to have ſeveral Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of divers Ages; but all the time of her living in this Place has been very private, not in the leaſt aſſociating herſelf with any of the Neighbourhood, or coming to Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but her Maid Servant would often be in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with ſome of the adjacent Neighbours Maids, being always very inquiſitive with them, but ſhe would never communicate any thing of her Miſtreſſes Domeſtick Affairs. The Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife herſelf was ſcarce ever ſeen in the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood, not ſo much as to ſtand at the Door, but ſteping into the Coach early in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and coming home in a Coach in the Night, and ſeldom or never were any Viſitants ſeen to come thither, but only ſome Gentlemen and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers often in the Evening or Night, except it were ſome of the Pariſh for the Kings Taxes, the Miniſters, Poor or other Duties, which ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, if ſhe hapen to be at home ſhe readily paid them at the Door, or ſent the Maid to them with the money and many compleſant Words; ſhe was obſerved to be often from home for ſeveral days together, yet ſo much was her maid ſervant her Confederate &amp; Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that the Affaires of the Houſe was kept ſo private and obſcure from the Neighbours, that they could not tell how many Children ſhe had in the Houſe, or how often changed, or otherwiſe diſpoſed of: <hi>Mrs. Crompton</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Fifty and Threeſcore Years of Age, and her maid has often declared upon ſeveral Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, That her miſtreſs has been a Midwife above Thirty Years; and 'tis generally ſaid that ſhe ſhe has followed this barbarous Infant mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murdering Trade ſo long, the truth of which is beſt known to the Omnipreſent God, the ſearcher of Hearts, who can bring the moſt hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Things of Darkneſs to light, and from whom no Secret is hid, who for Reaſons beſt known to his Providence, permits ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Sins to go before to Judgment, that is to be punished in this Life, and others to come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is, reſerved to the Tribunal of the great Day.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:151502:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Mrs. <hi>Crompton</hi> going out of Town the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the laſt Week, on <hi>Friday,</hi> pretty early in the Morning, the Maid-Servant (no doubt by the Order and Appointment of the Miſtriſs) left the Houſe likewiſe, leaving at home a Boyabout Seven Years of Age, and a Girl about Six Years Old, with a little Infant in the Cradle, leaving with them for Food on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a piece of Cheeſe and Water, not any Beer or Bread, but bid the Boy, in caſe the young Child cryed, to give it ſome Water, and ſhe would return in a little time; all which the Boy has ſince related: The Children continuing in the Houſe alone moſt part of the Day, and no Maid returning, grew very impatient, and particularly for want of Suſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Boy bringing of it into an outward Room next the Street, a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's Son paſſing by, and hearing the Child cry, called to the Boy to know what was the matter; to whom he declar'd, after ſome time, the Reaſons: That they were left all day alone in the Houſe, without Victuals, and that the young Child was almoſt ſtarved; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which, Neighbours being called, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable and Maſters of the Pariſh were ſent for, ſome of whom coming and entring the Houſe, examined the two Chilgren, who declared as before mentioned; and farther, beſides the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant in the Cradle, the Boy declared there were two more that lay Dead in a Hand-basket up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Shelf in the Cellar; another lay Buried in the Garden, and a Fourth in the Cellar: Upon preſent ſearch, they found the Two Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the Hand-basket as the Boy had ſaid, they being moſt lamentable Objects of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Miſery, looking at firſt ſight, were liker the Carkaſſes of Catts or Doggs than Humane Creatures, all their skin being off, as likewiſe their Eyes and part of their Fleſh eat with Vermin, ſtinking in a lamentable manner.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Monday</hi> being <hi>21ſt.</hi> Inſtant, the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roners Inqueſt were Impanell'd, and coming to the Houſe where the Dead Bodies lay in the Basket, after viewing of them, they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered ſome Labourers (according to the Words of the Boy) to Dig in ſeveral ſoft places of the Cellar where they perceived the ground had been broken, where, after ſome time, they Dug up ſix ſeveral Skeletons of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ſeveral Ages; upon which Night coming on, the Coroner Adjourn'd the Jury-till the next Day, reſolving to have the ground in the Garden likewiſe to be broken up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they brought in their Verdict, many of the Spectators took ſeveral of the Bones and carried them away, ſome of which are now to be ſeen at the <hi>Ben-Johnſon</hi>'s Head, near St. <hi>Brides</hi> Church by <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who were the Parents of theſe Children, or upon what account this Midwife had the keeping of them, is not certainly known, though it's generally conjectured, and that not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a great deal of Reaſon, that theſe were thoſe commonly called <hi>By-bl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> or <hi>Baſtards,</hi> which ſhe undertook, for a certain Sum of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney agreed on, to eaſe the Parents of, by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them as long as they lived. <hi>P. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>On Tueſday, Auguſt</hi> 22. This Day the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roner's Inqueſt met again, but were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed till <hi>Monday,</hi> on the Account that they had not done digging in the Garden, and other ports for Children, and for other Reaſons. This Day likewiſe about One in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, our Madam <hi>Compton,</hi> alias <hi>Norman,</hi> was Apprehended near <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> and with the Aſſiſtance of the Conſtables and Beadles, being led between two Men, attended with a numerous Croud of People; ſhe was carried to the Petty Seſſions of <hi>Bloomsbury,</hi> where ſhe was Examined before their Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace there ſitting; who likewiſe took ſeveral Affidavits, by which ſhe is vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuſpected (if not poſitively charged) to have Murthered ſeveral Children that were put to her to Nurſe; upon which ſhe was from thence Committed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> by the Warrant or Mittimus ſigned by the Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Juſtices of the Peace then on the Bench.</p>
            <p>When our Doughty Midwife was firſt ſeized, all the way ſhe went to the Juſtices, and when ſhe came before their Worſhips, ſhe was obſerved to carry her ſelf with a great deal of Confidence, not ſeeming in the leaſt concern'd, or much denying the Fact.</p>
            <p>At her firſt being in <hi>Newgate,</hi> She behaved her ſelf very very impudently, which grew afterwards into a fullenneſs; and juſt before the Seſſions that She expected to be Tryed, She fell ill: She was brought to the <hi>Old-Bayly</hi> tyed in a Chair, and carried on a Man's back, but the Court finding her very ill, the Tryal was put off till next Seſſions: She continues ſtill in a very languiſhing Condition, and ſeveral Phyſicians and other Ingenious Men that have been to viſit Her, give it as their Opinion, that they verily believe She has given her ſelf a Doſe of lingring Poyſon, as a <hi>French</hi> Midwife of <hi>Paris,</hi> did, on the like occaſion ſome years ſince.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for <hi>John Wallis</hi> near the <hi>Green Dragon T<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vern</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
